In 1987, Thomas Sankara, Burkina Faso´s president,
gave a speech against debt in the summit of the African Union.
The emancipation of its people and the freedom and development of the African
countries could only happen after the abolition of the historical debt to the west.
This revolutionary demand cost him his life.
We think that the debt has to be seen from the standpoint of its origins.
Debt’s origins come from colonialism’s origins.
Those who lend us money are those who had colonalized us before.
They are those who used to manage our states and economies.
Colonizers are those who indebted Africa
through their brothers and cousins.
We had no connections with this debt.
Therefore we cannot pay for it.
Debt is neo-colonialism, in which colonizers
transferred themselves into “technical assistant”.
We should better say “technical assassins”.
They present us with financing, with financial backers.
As if someone’s back could create development.
We have been advised to go to these lenders.
We have been proposed with nice financial set ups.
We have been indebted for 50, 60 years and even more.
That means we have been led to compromise
our people for fifty years and more.
Under its current form, that is imperialism controlled.
Debt is a cleverly managed re-conquest of Africa.